T. Thomas Boates papers, 1960-2022.
Congregational Library & Archives
T. Thomas Boates papers, 1960-2022.
MS5410
Congregational Library & Archives
1.09 Cubic Feet
(1 box)
Rev. T. Thomas Boates received a Bachelor of Divinity degree from Nazarene Theological School and a Master of Sacred Theology degree from Boston University School of Theology. Tom was the pastor at the East Baltimore Church of the Nazarene in Baltimore, Maryland, the North Congregational Church in Bedford, Massachusetts, and the First Federated Church in Beverly, Massachusetts. Tom joined the board of the American Congregational Association in 1997 and served as the Board Chair from 1999 until 2005. This collection contains records collected by T. Thomas Boates during the course of his work with New England churches and as a board member of the American Congregational Association and includes church annual reports, studies, documents related to mergers, and records relating to the maintenance and expansion of the Congregational House.
Boates, T. Thomas, Jr.
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library and Archive by Ellen B. Clark in February 2020 and September 2022; 2020-03, 2022-19.
Biographical note
Rev. T. Thomas Boates, often simply known as Tom, received a Bachelor of Divinity degree from Nazarene Theological School and a Master of Sacred Theology degree from Boston University School of Theology. He studied at Harvard Divinity School in the Ministry in the Vicinity program and was a Fellow at Yale Divinity School.
Tom was the pastor at the East Baltimore Church of the Nazarene in Baltimore, Maryland, the North Congregational Church in Bedford, Massachusetts, and the First Federated Church in Beverly, Massachusetts. He was also an Associate Pastor at Boston's Old South Church. He was the Area Conference Minister for the Metro Suffolk area of the New York Conference of the United Church of Christ. At Newton Theological School, he was the UCC Church Campaign Director.
Tom joined the board of the American Congregational Association in 1997. He became the Board Chair 1999 and served in that role until 2005. During his time on the board, Tom was instrumental in guiding the Congregational Library & Archives' transition to become a more modern and professionally staffed library. He continued to work with the board after his time as chair, especially as a member of the Board Development Committee.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records collected by T. Thomas Boates during the course of his work with New England churches and as a board member of the American Congregational Association. The church records Boates collected include reports, records related to mergers, studies, and annual reports. The American Congregational Association records are largely related to the maintenance of the Congregational House building and plans to expand the building.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the two series listed below. Within each series, materials have been arranged into chronological older by start date.
Series 1: Church records, 1960-2006
Series 1: American Congregational Association files, 1993-2022
Building management; Church records and registers.; American Congregational Association.; Central Congregational Church (Jamaica Plain, Boston, Mass.); Centre Congregational Church (Lynnfield, Mass.); First Congregational Church (Chester, Mass.); First Congregational Church (East Longmeadow, Mass.); First Congregational Church (Gardner, Mass.); First Congregational Church (Hyde Park, Boston, Mass.); First Congregational Church (Reading, Mass.); First Congregational Church in Exeter (Exeter, N.H.); First Congregational Church in Worcester (Worcester, Mass.); Memorial Congregational Church (North Quincy, Quincy, Mass.); Mt. Vernon Congregational Church (Boston, Mass.); Old North Church (Marblehead, Mass.); Pilgrim United Church of Christ (New Bedford, Mass.); Quincy Point Congregational Church (Quincy, Mass.); South Congregational Church (Springfield, Mass.); St. Mark's Congregational Church (Roxbury, Boston, Mass.); Trinitarian Congregational Church (Concord, Mass.); Union Congregational Church (Wollaston, Quincy, Mass.); United Church of Christ. New Hampshire Conference; United Parish of Auburndale (Auburndale, Newton, Mass.); West Concord Union Church (Concord, Mass.); West Parish Church (Andover, Mass.)
- Church records, 1960 2006; 1960-2006; 24 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains church records gathered by Boates from churches he worked at or with. The series contains annual reports, survey results and reports, meeting minutes, clippings, and records related to various church mergers.
  - Pilgrim United Church of Christ (New Bedford) merger records, 1960 1964; 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Shrewsbury: A Church Extension Analysis, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Central Congregational Church (Jamaica Plain, Boston) records, 1980 1991; 1980-1991 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - St. Mark Congregational Church (Roxbury, Boston) records, 1980 1985; 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - First Congregational Church (Gardner) records, 1980 1985; 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Report of the task force for the study of human sexuality, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Congregational Church in Exeter, New Hampshire, records, 1984 1990; 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Union Congregational Church and Memorial Congregational Church merger records, 1984 1985; 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Union Congregational Church and Memorial Congregational Church merger records, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - First Congregational Church (Reading) annual report, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - West Parish Church (Andover) reports, 1985 1986; 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - First Congregational Church (East Longmeadow) records, 1985 1987; 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - United Parish of Aburndale records, 1985 1991; 1985-1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - First Congregational Church (Hyde Park, Boston) records, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - First Congregational Church in Worcester survey reports, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - South Church (Springfield) records, 1986 1989; 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Centre Congregational Church (Lynnfield) records, 1986 1996; 1986-1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - New Hampshire Conference records, 1989 1992; 1989-1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Old North Church (Marblehead) records, 1989 1992; 1989-1992 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Trinitarian Congregational Church (Concord) records, 1990 1991; 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - West Concord Union Church constitution, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Quincy Point Congregational Church annual reports, 1995 1997; 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Congregational Church of Chester 275th anniversary program, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mount Vernon Congregational Church (Boston) annual meeting, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- American Congregational Association files, 1993 2022; 1993-2022; 7 Folders
  This series contains records relating to Boates's work as a board member of the American Congregational Association. The series includes committee meeting minutes, especially those of the building committee, records related the alley, and communications.
  Related Materials
  Materials in this collection are likely duplicative of records found within the American Congregational Association records, 1846-2022, RG4360, held by the Congregational Library & Archives.
  - Climate control system, 1993 2002; 1993-2002 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Alley legal opinions, 1999 2004; 1999-2004 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Building committee records, 2000 2005; 2000-2005 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Communications, 2001 2005; 2001-2005 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Building enhancement task force records, 2004 2005; 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Notes, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Boates plaque, 2022 (Box 1, Folder 31)